Hello, welcome back to our course, and today we are going to talk about R Markdown reports. Alright, so why R Markdown? Well, it helps us create a document that embeds both text and code,
and there are several advantages: Research becomes more reproducible, makes it easier to share analysis results together with documentation.
When you knit the document, the code is executed, and the output appears alongside text. And the document renders only if there are no errors
and then you can render the document to HTML, PDF, or Word. So if you are not in RStudio, so basically you can install R Markdown by using this tinytex
and then rmarkdown packages. And then this pandoc is our swiss-army knife to convert files from one markup format to another.
But if you are in R studio, then basically what do you need to do? You need to click file, and then you need to go
to new file, and then to R markdown. And then you can see this dialog box, and you can see that you can select the title, the author, and then the output format.
All right, so this is a default file, you can see that,
basically, there are two chunks. There's this chunk with, the title, author, output, and date, and there are other chunks, it's like R chunk, and then there's a text.
And we are going to go through all these chunks today. So, the first chunk is basically this YAML chunk. So YAML is a human-readable data format,
not markup, and the name is "YAML Ain't Markup Language". Originally, it was "Yet Another Markup Language".
And then we have a markdown. So here, that
language was defined by Gruber and Swartz. And it's a lightweight markup language with plain text formatting syntax, and can be converted to many output formats.
And then we have R markdown, so this is the integration of R code into Markdown documents, and here we have a cheat sheet
with many R markdown related things, so you can see that this is the header,
and this is our R markdown with code chunks. Alright, so this is the YAML excerpt, so basically here we have a few elements, so
how do we start a blog? How do we start a comment? How do we start a list with certain elements? Here we have in-line item lists, then we have a named list,
and then we have a few other keys. So here under these links, you are going to find some methods to convert R data to YAML and back.
Okay, so this is an example header. This is our header of our document, and then you can see that, actually
if I study the attributes of that header, I can see that that header now,
it's a list of four elements with a title, with an author, with date, and output.
And how did I study it? Well, I needed to first upload this
library, YAML, and then I applied the function read_yaml. Another header here
for a vignette, for example, so we have a title, once again, we have an author
with two elements, name and email, we also have a date here, and this is an inline R code, which evaluates
at each knit time. And then we have an output,
I would like to have it in HTML document, and I would like to have
table of contents, so toc true. And then there are some, other options for, R package vignette metadata.
And once again, I could use this read_yaml from R
package, and you can see that now these lists look slightly different, so we have 5 elements,
and then we have a title, we have an author, and then the author is actually also a list of two elements, etc.
But of course, now we have
many options for output formats. For example, we can have an HTML notebook,
HTML document, PDF document, Word document, beamer presentation, PowerPoint presentation, etc.
So, of course, we choose the option we would like to do in that particular moment. For example, I'm using for this course
beamer presentation. And then, of course, for details, you can have a look at the sling, and then there are more options and more formats.
When it comes to rendering, how do we render a PDF document? So basically, actually, we go through
Rmd, then there is, knitr, then it's transformed to md. From md, we go through pandoc to tex, and from tex
through PDF, LaTeX to PDF. So, beamer is a LaTex document class for creating presentation slides.
And then here, you have additional options only for PDFs, for example like toc_depth. So the lowest level of headings
to add to table of contents. But you have also some special options only for beamer.
So here we have color theme, or for example, a slide_level, which is the lowest heading level that defines
individual slides. And of course, it's all up to you how you'd like to customize your document.
And then some further options, rendering options. You can see that the list is long, but instead of me reading through all these options,
I really suggest that you try yourself on RStudio, create new R markdown document, and play with these options. I think this is the best way to learn programming, just actually by doing it.
What I would like to show you today is actually an example of that YAML header, so basically how I would like
my beamer presentation to look like. For this particular deck of slides, you can see that I have a title, I have a subtitle, I have an author, then I didn't want to have any date,
then for the output, I wanted to have a beamer presentation, I wanted to keep
tex file associated with that presentation, and I would like to have
the syntax highlighted in that zenburn. Then my header also includes
this line with user package, so basically I created a special customized theme for this course.
Then I would like to also hide beamer's navigation buttons. And then I would like to have these
slide numbers in the footer. And then a few options for
the color of the links, and the color of citations.
Okay, let me stop here, and we are going to come back to R Markdown and text formatting in the next video.